welcome to meditating with john verveiki
we do this live stream every weekday
morning at 9 30 a.m with mondays
alternating between a new lesson dharma
day
and review of the whole ecology of
practices papaya day
due to a scheduling issue there will be
no live stream
next tuesday next tuesday if you're
joining us for the first time welcome
please continue to meet with us but what
i recommend you do is go
to uh the description for this video and
you'll find links to previous lessons
and sits
do lesson one immediately and then every
week do one or two more lessons and soon
you'll be integrated with us
i would ask you all to please like this
stream to increase its visibility on the
youtube algorithm
at the end of every session there is a q
a
please limit your questions uh to
anything from
the whole entire ecology practices for
more encompassing questions
uh please join us on the live stream
on youtube general question general q a
um 3 p.m eastern every third friday of
the month
in addition to your questions i please
encourage everybody to share their
observations
and their comments this helps all of us
do the practice
so i think that's everything right now
so we're doing part three
of the walking meditation i'll just do a
quick review of the basics and then
today i'm going to put
uh time into reviewing especially the
turning
so we start
right foot goes 45 degrees hip width
we step 70 of our weight forward knee
over the center of our foot
not past our toes we're not leaning
we're not leaning back we're keeping a
bend in both knees
weight goes forward we exhale weight
goes i'll put my hands here so you can
see my hips
go back pivot 45 align the knee
turn even more no weight no weight on my
right foot bring my right foot up and
then turn my hips as i come forward
and then back turn out 45 degrees align
the knee
turn and then come forward
okay so and as you remember we're
exhaling as
like here inhaling exhaling
inhaling exhale
we're meditating we're we're meditating
on the flow of the breath because
it is the metronome for the walking
meditation
but we're also meditating on maintaining
an active
presence of being centered and rooted
okay so the turning i'll do it both
directions so let's say
we're here okay so you see my foot
so my weight i'm going to bring my
weight back and i'm going to come up so
whenever i
walk whenever i'm going forward it's
remember it's tiger paw heel to toe as
my weight goes down
i go heel to toe so i go back i come up
onto the heel
i pivot as far as i can my weight is
still all on my
back leg i don't put this foot down
because i can pivot it more if i shift
my weight
see as i'm shifting my weight i can
pivot it even more so as i shift my
weight from my back to my front leg i
can pivot even more
then i shift my weight onto this leg and
i bring this leg
up and over get that hip width and now
back
now back that's what does it look like
on this side
so i'm here right
my weight goes back and i pivot as much
as i can we'll keep
you can draw your weight see see how the
weight and the foot
are turning as much as i can but i don't
put that foot down
because as i shift my weight from my
back leg to my front leg
i can pivot even more i can let this my
front foot begin to pivot to take the
strain off this hip
and then it comes up and over
okay so back pivoting
then shifting and pivoting more up
and over and you can push
this heel back a little bit to get the
proper alignment if you need to
the back heel so back
back and drawing and shifting
and turning even more up and over
here back foot comes up
i pivot it don't put the foot down
right drawing all the way to this side
then pivoting even more
as i shift my weight and then up and
over
so again back
okay back
shift like i said let this foot slide a
bit if you need to
don't put too much pressure on your knee
or your head and then up and over
see how i actually lift it off the
ground get it into position
and then forward and push this heel back
a little bit if i need to so i get it
back to the 45 degrees
i'll do it two more times on each side
and then we will move to this practice
back pivoting
over
okay i hope that's helpful review and
eventually we're going to add in the
arms and i'll show you what that looks
like
not because i expect you to practice it
because just get the get the footwork
down is really important
so how we actually start in the practice
is we start with this foot at the right
foot
at the 45 degrees to the right
and just on the ball of the foot behind
the toes here
and we get we turn our we turn to our
right this hand comes in front
this hand comes up and forward like this
back align
shift back right
align here and then a turn
here okay it's called brush knees
and when you add in the arms this
becomes a fully embodied
very engaging very absorbing form of
mindful movement and so we'll work next
week we'll work towards adding the arms
in
and then you'll have a very significant
uh moving practice that you can do
uh and then you will do always do the
moving practice first
then come into the standing chi kung
then go into the seated qigong do the
chanting
and then going go into uh the silence
sit
okay i'm just going to go off camera for
a sec to get
my map
that's good thank you jason
all right so
i encourage you all to keep practicing
with the walking meditation
eventually we'll get you to full-blown
brush knees
um it takes time uh because you're
learning a practice
that is has been designed over centuries
uh to really engage the cerebellum
cortex loop
really enhance your centering and
routing and your balance both physical
and mental
and give you a practice that will induce
flow
and absorption and also
get your brain very used to doing
mindfulness within a very involved and
engrossing
movement action
you can actually fight with that move in
self-defense
okay so that helps to bridge
between your sitted practice and your
everyday life
all right so let's get into position
let's set our phones on do not disturb
uh we will begin when i say begin and we
will
start with chanting
[Music]
begins
one
[Music]
oh
one
on
oh
[Laughter]
one
oh
[Music]
one
[Laughter]
[Music]
begin your silent set
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate with your
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communities
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
so
so let's take some questions you're
always welcome um
so first is from mark always
uh great to have you here mark can you
say more about the interstage as it
relates to my struggle with the
psychological narratives i mentioned
previously how is the inner sage
to be used uh to help um
so in the deepest sense
the inner sage helps you by getting you
to
reorient your process
of i of identity formation excuse me
so if you'll allow me to use uh some
spatial metaphors and this this will
come out especially mark
when we talk about stoicism and i talked
about it in the
um awakening for the meeting crisis
narrative
is your historical horizontal
way of being and of course we need to do
this because we have to pursue long-term
goals or in a developmental trajectory
etc
the inner sage reminds you
that you are not to be finally
identified with your narratives
that beyond the autobiographical self
there is the ontological self the inner
sage
directs you off of the autobiography
and onto the owner's manual if i can put
it that way
and not as just an act of intellectual
reflection
as an act of identification
you start to find the home for yourself
in the ontology of your of your being
rather than in the narrative and this is
what all these practices are doing
they're getting you to become aware of
all the levels
all the layers
of who and what you are how you emerge
out
of the of the environment and your body
and your mind and your spirit
by that i mean your capacity for
self-transcendence i don't mean anything
supernatural
bringing those all into an aligned
awareness which of course
means aligning the four kinds of knowing
so that they are actively mutually
affording each other
creates a different sense of
identification
that gives us a space of freedom from
the narratives
not to despise them or dispense with
them
but to no longer be confused with them
so that they lose some of
the way they can cut us and catch us
and that's when the inner sage comes
into your awareness
it is the inner sage is offering you a
new way of being
and right as i said rather than just the
autobiographical self
we're now talking about the ontological
self
and this is the self that
the stoics will argue is ultimately
how we respond to the sufferings of life
the stoics will argue that this we
we have to do our best and morally and
right and as much as we can
and unfolding this but ultimately
our ability to alter the world is
very small compared to
our ability to transform
who would what we are ontologically we
have very
little control over
the length of this we can do things to
improve our health and improve
our you know the like our longevity and
all kinds of things
but we are ultimately not gods
we are finally deeply finite beings
but we can find
and so there's a sense in which this
cannot come to
a completion if we identify with it we
will always ultimately be frustrated
but we can find a depth of being
that is completely satisfying
that's anorexia such that we can live
with the finitude and the fate of
our mortal existence
so that's an answer to your question i
hope it's
i hope it's helpful and we will get into
more of this
uh when we do uh uh wisdom of foundation
we do stoicism
uh rain rainer lutvik hi rayner it's
good to have you here
during meditative questing i always go
down to a rabbit hole with a few
negative experiences which i would
rather like to forget
any ideas on how to approach regretful
painful memories
well first of all um they you
keep remembering them because they have
not been fully processed
this is sort of a standard almost cliche
but i think it is a
uh a valuable psychodynamic trip um
there more processing needs to be done
that material um
it needs to go from being always relived
to remembered when needed
and so part of what we can do
remember when i talked about encoding
specificity that we tend to
not only remember the event or the facts
and this also relates to what i just
said about stoicism by the way
we also remember deeply the state of
being we are
in when we're remembering this fact or
that event
and that's why stoicism paying more
attention to the state of being
is ultimately where you have the most as
epictetus as
the most control but
back to rainer's point so
often the way we try to learn
from a situation that's painful is
we learn it using some very primitive
primitive forms of processing
very you know automatic reactive
emotional
processing and then and then how we try
to learn our lesson is we learn it with
pain
and with guilt and guilt is a kind of
psychological pain
we inflict on ourselves we basically are
punishing ourselves
to try and direct our behavior now
you you know there's a sense in which
learning
start has to start at that level because
we're not initially
linguistic beings we're not a list
initially rationally reflected beings
etc but what this tradition
proposes is can you
bring up the painful situation
perhaps by being in a stance of meta
towards it
and then instead right
instead of trying to avoid the guilt can
you transmute it can you let the guilt
come up
and then instead of trying to get away
from it or trying to instantly resolve
it
open up the processing and try to
replace the guilt with what's
transmuted don't replace it sorry that
was a mistake on my part
you want to transmute it into
what's called intelligent regret if you
were trying to correct
the behavior of a good friend
you wouldn't hurt them to correct their
behavior
or you try to minimize the hurt you
wouldn't
inflict pain or even guilt on them
other than the minimal force desire to
bring about
recognition and response minimal force
required to bring about recognition and
response
so the guilt is there to help get you
you recognizing and responding
but that's not enough to finish the
process you bring in intelligent regret
what do you do with your friend you try
to open up their thinking
you try to explicate you know how does
this sit in the larger context
what you try to do is replace a very
primitive and childish state of being
that is your recognition and response of
the event that is painful
with an adult recognition and response
to the event that is painful
so you need to process these and the
kind of processing isn't just
processing the facts it's processing you
you we
all we all need to do this you have to
grow up
chore in how you are recognizing and
responding
yes the pain and the guilt get you into
the initial recognition and response
but then move into intelligent regret
talk to yourself talk to the
talk to yourself as you would to
a beloved friend this is kind of what's
going on in
what's called um internal family systems
uh therapy and what you do is you
basically are growing up
the person that is recognizing and
responding to the thing you're not
trying to acknowledge it you're not
sorry you're not
you're acknowledging you're not trying
to ignore it and get away from it but
you're not just staying locked
into who you are this is why this is
ultimately an extension of meta
you unlock who you are by growing up
maturing how you are recognizing and
responding
to the event so i hope that's helpful to
you
uh kira welcome kira and thank you for
some of the encouraging things you've
been saying
in your comments they are very much
appreciated
i've never got a lot from meditative
questing a member of the sangha talked
about how they have been questing on who
i am in relationship
to i have found that very rich thoughts
that's great that's excellent
um so what you're doing here
and this is to complement you you're
integrating
meditative questing which is a way of
deepening vipassana
with aspects of meta and that that
that's natural
you see what's happening here what's
happening is you're
this is your inner teacher your inner
sage trying to draw you towards prajna
are bringing the two more and more into
an integrated processing
keep doing that that is a good
intuition to follow upon
uh uh stan tolpranit i've i've
got to speak to you a couple times that
lowest over video i hope you're doing
well
um just wanted to say this walking
meditation is probably exactly what i
need to
well get forward i'm too much in my head
in and from and for the intellect so
thanks
you're welcome that's exactly the intent
of it it is to
sati deeply remember that we
are deeply embodied embedded
beings okay
so yeah and try
for though and be really gentle on
yourself but
also try to hear what i'm going to say a
lot of the the resistance you might have
to this
is it's just hard it's hard and i get
that and that's why i keep encouraging
you
i keep reverting reviewing i keep
responding to questions and concerns
about it
but on the other part of it is
trying to note if at any point and i
don't want to
get too probative because
you're all just learning but there's
also there there's also an aspect
of i found this in myself at least when
i was learning
there's a resistance to this precisely
because it gets me
out of my head and there's a part of me
that doesn't want to get out of my head
because i like being in my head because
john is so
smart right and look at all the things
john can do
and look at how he can you know make
people smile at him and he's so clever
and getting out of that especially into
oh
john's kind of clumsy as he's moving in
his body
but that's really where he's at
that's really the depths of his being i
didn't like that
but it was ultimately so good for me
so good for me
okay i want to thank you all for joining
i want to of course thank my dear friend
of techno major maher
and my beloved son jason who's behind
the scenes making everything work with
the camera
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
uh you'll find links to the lecture
series awakening from the meaning crisis
and to the dialogue series of voices
with verveiki
where these themes and related themes
are explored in depth and
situated and honed within a more
encompassing
way of life invite others who might
benefit by sharing this series
please join the discord server to chat
with others to practice with others
there's links in the description
i encourage you next tuesday uh to meet
as a sangha on the discord
server it's just a wonderful growing
vital community
we do this every weekday morning at 9 30
eastern time
there's no stream on tuesday due to
scheduling
please remember that continuity of
practice is more important than sure
quantity of practice
there is no enemy
no obstacle worse than your own minded
body
but there's no friend no ally no true
companion on
the path better than your own mind and
body
be lamps unto yourselves and to each
other
i'll see you all on monday for you pie
day take good care everyone